<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Glenn L. Nielsen</author>
    <title>Reporting Bugs</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

<section name="Before you report a bug">
<p>The Apache Tomcat community consists of those who use Apache Tomcat, help answer
questions on discussions lists, contribute documentation and patches,
and those who develop and maintain the code for Apache Tomcat.  Almost all those
who assist on a day to day basis resolving bug reports do this for a
wide variety of reasons, and almost all of them do this on their own time.</p>

<p>Many bugs reported end up not being a bug in the Apache Tomcat code, but are
due to misconfiguration, problems caused by installed applications, the
operating system, etc.</p>

<div style="margin-left: 2em">
  <p><b>Before reporting a bug please make every effort to resolve the problem
  yourself.</b></p>

  <p>If you need help, ask on the <b>users</b>
   <a href="lists.html#tomcat-users">mailing list</a>.</p>
</div>

<p>The remainder of this document points you toward resources you can use to
resolve the problem you are having.
</p>

  <subsection name="Bugzilla is not a support forum">
  <p>Bugzilla is a tool to track bug reports and feature requests. It is used
    to <b>organize</b> work on Apache Tomcat projects, so that such issues are not
    forgotten and to document how they were resolved.
  </p>

  <p>Bugzilla <b>is not</b> a place to ask questions on how to configure your
    own system, or how to interpret some error message or behaviour that you
    do not understand. If you have questions, please ask on the <b>users</b>
    <a href="lists.html#tomcat-users">mailing list</a>.
  </p>

  <p>When you have gathered enough information to diagnose your problem,
    and it is indeed a bug that can be fixed in Apache Tomcat, feel
    free to create or reopen your Bugzilla issue for it. You can find a link to
    your discussion in the <a href="lists.html">mailing list archives</a>
    and include it in your bug report.
  </p>
  </subsection>
</section>


<section name="Resources to help resolve Apache Tomcat problems">
<p>Here are some resources you can use to help you resolve the
problem you are having before reporting a bug.</p>

  <subsection name="Problem troubleshooting">
    <ul>
    <li><b>Documentation</b> &#x2013; Review the documentation for the version
      of Apache Tomcat that you are using.  The problem that you are
      facing may already be addressed in the docs.  Note, that documentation
      is searchable.</li>
    <li><b>Logs</b> &#x2013; The logs which Apache Tomcat generates can be a valuable
      resource when trying to diagnose a problem.  Please review them.
      You may want to enable debug output in your Apache Tomcat configuration
      so that you have more information to help diagnose the problem.
      You may want to configure an Access Log (a valve) to log what requests
      reached Tomcat and what was Tomcat's response to them.
    </li>
    <li><b>Wiki</b> &#x2013; Search the
      <a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/FrontPage">Wiki</a>.
      That is unofficial documentation to which everyone can contribute.
    </li>
    <li><b>FAQ's</b> &#x2013; Search the <a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/FAQ">
      Tomcat Frequently Asked Questions</a> that is part of the Wiki.</li>
    </ul>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Apache Tomcat discussion lists">
    <p>It is very likely you are not the first to run into a problem.
      Others may have already found a solution. The mailing list archives may
      contain discussions which will help you resolve the problem.
    </p>
    <p>See the <a href="lists.html">mailing lists</a> page for the further
    information on the lists.</p>
    <p>See also the <a href="findhelp.html">Find help</a> page.</p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Known issues">
    <p>Please search the bug database to see if the bug you are seeing has
       already been reported. Please look at the changelog page for the bugs
       that have already been fixed. The changelogs for not-yet-released
       versions of Tomcat are also available. More details are below.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Recent version">
    <p>Try to reproduce your problem with the latest released version of
    Apache Tomcat.</p>

  </subsection>
</section>

<section name="Looking for known issues">

  <subsection name="Search the bug database">
    <p>Please search the bug database to see if the bug you are
      seeing has already been reported.
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>The bug may have already been fixed and is available in a later
      version or nightly build.</li>
      <li>Someone else may have reported the bug, you could add supporting
      information to help reproduce and resolve the bug.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The search page is
      <a href="https://bz.apache.org/bugzilla/query.cgi">here</a>.
      There is also
      <a href="https://bz.apache.org/bugzilla/query.cgi?format=advanced">advanced</a>
      search page.
    </p>
    <p>Here are some search tips.</p>
    <ol>
      <li><p>Search for closed bugs as well as for the open ones.</p>
        <p>On the advanced search page you can clear the "Status" field to
        avoid filtering by status.</p>
      </li>
      <li><p>Search across different versions of Tomcat.</p>
        <p>In the bug database Tomcat is represented by several "products".
        The same problem should be reported only once, but the fix may
        be applied to different Tomcat versions. While doing so, the bug report
        is moved between different products. A bug that is originally
        reported against Tomcat 9 is moved to Tomcat 8 and maybe later to
        Tomcat 7. So it makes sense to search all the versions at once.</p>

        <p>Here is a quick list of supported products:</p>
        <ul>
         <li><b>Tomcat 9</b>, <b>Tomcat 8</b> and <b>Tomcat 7</b>
             &#x2013; Tomcat 9.0.x, 8.5.x or 8.0.x and 7.0.x</li>
         <li><b>Tomcat Connectors</b> &#x2013; Integration of Tomcat with other Web servers</li>
         <li><b>Tomcat Native</b> &#x2013; APR based native HTTP and AJP connectors for Tomcat</li>
         <li><b>Tomcat Modules</b> &#x2013; Additional Tomcat components</li>
         <li><b>Taglibs</b> &#x2013; Apache <a href="/taglibs/">Taglibs</a> subproject</li>
       </ul>

      </li>
      <li><p>Search not only Summary field, but also the Comment one</p>
        <p>On the advanced search page open "Detailed Bug Information",
          then type your query into the "Comment" field.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li><p>You can limit results to the issues that were changed recently.</p>
        <p>On the advanced search page open "Search by Change History",
        then type "<code>-2m</code>" into the first field in the pair of
        "between" fields to limit results to the issues changed in the last
        2 months.</p>
      </li>
      <li><p>Some bugs do not belong to Tomcat.</p>
        <p>Tomcat bundles libraries from several other projects. You can see
        RELEASE-NOTES and NOTICE files in your distribution for details. More
        details are in a separate section below.</p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Changelog">

    <p>If you are looking for the recently fixed issues there are several
       places to look at.</p>

    <ul>
      <li><p>Changelog files for released versions</p>
        <p>These are published on the Tomcat website.</p>
      </li>
      <li><p>Changelog files for <em>not-yet-released</em> versions</p>
        <p>These are available in the source code.</p>
        <p>They are in XML format with style sheets attached. Thus
          modern web browsers can display them nicely.</p>
        <p>The files are also available in nightly documentation builds.
          See <a href="ci.html">Buildbot</a> page for details.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>Links:</p>

    <table class="detail-table">
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Product</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Changelog (released)</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Changelog (unreleased)</strong></th>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Tomcat 9.0 (trunk)</td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-9.0-doc/changelog.html">changelog.html</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/trunk/webapps/docs/changelog.xml">changelog.xml</a>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Tomcat 8.5</td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-8.5-doc/changelog.html">changelog.html</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/tc8.5.x/trunk/webapps/docs/changelog.xml">changelog.xml</a>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Tomcat 8.0</td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-8.0-doc/changelog.html">changelog.html</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/tc8.0.x/trunk/webapps/docs/changelog.xml">changelog.xml</a>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Tomcat 7.0</td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-7.0-doc/changelog.html">changelog.html</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/tc7.0.x/trunk/webapps/docs/changelog.xml">changelog.xml</a>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Tomcat Connectors</td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/connectors-doc/miscellaneous/changelog.html">changelog.html</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/jk/trunk/xdocs/miscellaneous/changelog.xml">changelog.xml</a>
      </td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Tomcat Native</td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/native-doc/miscellaneous/changelog.html">changelog.html</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/native/branches/1.1.x/xdocs/miscellaneous/changelog.xml">changelog.xml</a>
      </td>
    </tr>
    </table>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Third party components">
    <p>Tomcat bundles libraries from several other projects. See
    RELEASE-NOTES and NOTICE files in your distribution for details. The
    versions of the components that were used to build Tomcat are defined
    in the <code>build.properties.default</code> file in the source
    distribution.</p>

    <p>Notable components are:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><p>Tomcat service launcher &#x2013;
          <code>commons-daemon-*</code>, <code>tomcatN.exe</code>,
          <code>tomcatNw.exe</code>
        </p>
        <p>The service launcher is provided by
          <a href="http://commons.apache.org/daemon/">Apache Commons Daemon</a>
          project.</p>
        <p>Using the terminology from that project, the *nixes launcher is
          called <code>jsvc</code> and the Windows launcher is called
         <code>procrun</code>. The <code>tomcatN.exe</code> and
         <code>tomcatNw.exe</code> programs in Tomcat distributions
         are just renamed <code>prunsrv.exe</code> and <code>prunmgr.exe</code>
         from Apache Commons Daemon binaries distribution.
      </p>
      </li>

      <li><p>DBCP Database Pool implementation &#x2013;
          <code>tomcat-dbcp.jar</code>.
        </p>
        <p>This pool implementation is provided by
          <a href="http://commons.apache.org/pool/">Apache Commons Pool</a>
          and
          <a href="http://commons.apache.org/dbcp/">Apache Commons DBCP</a>
          projects.</p>
        <p>The classes from these two projects are renamed into a different
          package, to avoid conflicts if the same libraries are used by web
          applications, recompiled and packed into a single JAR file.</p></li>

      <li><p>JDBC Database Pool implementation &#x2013;
          <code>tomcat-jdbc.jar</code>.
        </p>
        <p>This pool implementation is available with Tomcat 7 and later and
          it comes from <b>jdbc-pool</b> project that
          is part of <b>Tomcat Modules</b>.
          This library is developed alongside the main Tomcat.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li><p>Tomcat
        <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/maven-plugin.html">Maven plugin</a>
        subproject tracks its issues in
        <a href="https://bz.apache.org/jira/browse/MTOMCAT">JIRA database</a>.
        </p>
       </li>

<!-- Maybe mention these later. I am not sure about wording.
       <li><p>Tomcat redistributions by various Linux vendors</p>
         <p>Some of them provide notably outdated versions of Apache Tomcat.</p>
       </li>
 -->
     </ul>
  </subsection>

</section>

<section name="Reporting Apache Tomcat bugs">
<p>Please make sure the problem is a bug in Apache Tomcat and not a
bug in your web application.</p>
<p>Note, that <a href="security.html">security-related</a> issues should
<b>not</b> be reported through Bugzilla.</p>

  <subsection name="How to write a bug report">
  <p>Please provide as much information as possible. It is
    very hard to fix a bug if the person looking into the problem cannot
    reproduce it. See also
    <a href="https://bz.apache.org/bugzilla/page.cgi?id=bug-writing.html">Bug Writing Guidelines</a>.
  </p>

  <p>Bug submission starts
    <a href="https://bz.apache.org/bugzilla/enter_bug.cgi">here</a>.
    You have to include the following information in your bug report:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><p><b>Product</b>. Here is a list of supported products:</p>
    <ul>
     <li><b>Tomcat 9</b> &#x2013; Tomcat 9.0.x and tomcat.apache.org web site</li>
     <li><b>Tomcat 8</b> &#x2013; Tomcat 8.5.x and 8.0.x</li>
     <li><b>Tomcat 7</b> &#x2013; Tomcat 7.0.x</li>
     <li><b>Tomcat Connectors</b> &#x2013; Integration of Tomcat with other Web servers.
       The <b>mod_jk</b> module for <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache HTTPD</a>
       and other web servers.</li>
     <li><b>Tomcat Native</b> &#x2013; HTTP and AJP connectors for Tomcat
       using native code and linked with Apache APR and OpenSSL libraries</li>
     <li><b>Tomcat Modules</b> &#x2013; Additional Tomcat components, such as <b>jdbc-pool</b></li>
     <li><b>Taglibs</b> &#x2013; Apache <a href="/taglibs/">Taglibs</a> subproject</li>
   </ul>
    </li>
    <li><p><b>Version</b> &#x2013; Apache Tomcat version.</p>
      <p>Please not only select it from the list, but also mention it in
      your text. The bug description can be updated, so it is important
      to mention the version in the text as well.
      </p></li>
    <li><p><b>Component</b> &#x2013; The component which has the bug.</p>
      <p>If you do not know, just guess.</p></li>
    <li><p><b>Platform</b> and <b>OS</b> &#x2013; Hardware platform and
      operating system Tomcat is running on.</p></li>
    <li><p><b>Severity</b> &#x2013; This is <code>normal</code> for usual
      bug reports and <code>enhancement</code> for enhancement requests.</p>
      <p>If you tend to mark it as <code>critical</code>, you are probably
      doing it wrong. It is likely that the issue is already known and fixed,
      or it is not an issue at all.</p>
    </li>
    <li><p>Configuration details</p>
      <p>Please mention these in your text:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Java version &#x2013; Vendor and version of your Java
          Runtime Environment used to run Tomcat.</li>
        <li>If Tomcat is used behind
          <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache HTTPD</a> or other web
          server &#x2013; its version and how it is configured.</li>
        <li>Tomcat Connector that is being used.
          There are several implementations of Connectors in Tomcat.
          Which one is being used is shown in the logs during Tomcat startup.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><p>Attachments</p>
      <p>Attach configuration files and Tomcat log files if they would help
         to track down the bug.</p>
    </li>
    <li><p>Reproducer</p>
      <p>Please describe how to reproduce your problem on a clean Tomcat
         installation.
         If you can please provide a <b>simple</b> sample web application
         that demonstrates the issue.
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="How to submit patches and enhancement requests">
  <p>Enhancement requests for Tomcat are submitted using the same procedure
    as bug reports, but in the <b>Severity</b> field you will select the value
    "<code>enhancement</code>".
  </p>

  <p>To propose a patch, attach it to a Bugzilla issue. 
    When providing a patch, please mention to which version of the source code it
    applies. Any patches are welcome, but we prefer the ones that use the
    <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diff#Unified_format" rel="nofollow">
    Unified Diff</a> format. Those can be generated using <code>diff -u</code>
    command or <code>svn diff</code> or <code>git diff</code> command.
  </p>

  <p>To patch and build Apache Tomcat see the following references:</p>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="svn.html">Subversion repository structure</a> of Apache Tomcat</li>
    <li>Read BUILDING.txt in the source distribution</li>
  </ul>

  <p>To prepare a documentation patch:</p>

  <p>Read section on building the documentation in BUILDING.txt file
  in the source distribution.
  Usually the documentation for a version of Tomcat is located in
  <code>webapps/docs/</code> directory in the source code and
  can be built with <code>ant build-docs</code> command.</p>

  <p>To build documentation it should be sufficient to have a Java runtime
  and a copy of <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant</a>. Compiling
  Tomcat code should be unnecessary.
  </p>

  <p>Generic references:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><p>Apache Software Foundation guildelines:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>General <a href="http://www.apache.org/dev/version-control.html#anon-svn">Apache
        guidance for Subversion</a></li>
        <li>Sending in Patches chapter of
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/dev/contributors.html#patches">Contributors Tech Guide</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><p>General Subversion documentation:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The <a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/index.en.html">Subversion Book</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  </subsection>

<subsection name="Security Issues">
<p>Security-related bugs are of special concern.  If you have a verified
security bug to report please neither post it
to public email lists nor submit a bug report.
See <a href="security.html">Security Reports</a> page on how to report them.</p>
</subsection>

</section>

</body>
</document>
