<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>TomcatCon</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="TomcatCon">

<img src="/res/images/tomcatcon-london-2017.jpg" width="100%"/>

<subsection name="When">

<p>26 September 2017</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Where">

<p>Hilton Doubletree, Westminster, London, UK</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="What">

<p>TomcatCon London is the place for all users of Tomcat to expand their Tomcat
   knowledge in areas such as networking, security, performance and deployment.
   It also offers an opportunity to discuss the current Tomcat roadmap and
   help inform future development.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/tomcatcon-london-2017-tickets-36683639754">Registration</a>
   for TomcatCon London is now open.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Schedule">

<ul>
<li>08.00 Registration and Breakfast</li>
<li>09.00 Welcome<br/>
    Introduction and Welcome from our event sponsor, Liferay</li>
<li>09.20 State of the Cat<br/>
    Mark Thomas (markt)<br/>
    A review of the past year or so for Apache Tomcat and a look forward to what
    is expected in the coming 12 months. In particular, this will include the
    progress of Tomcat 9 towards its first stable release.</li>
<li>10.20 New and upcoming<br/>
    Rémy Maucherat (remm)<br/>
    In this session Rémy will discuss the features recently added to Tomcat as
    well as new features currently being considered including HTTP/2, NIO,
    suspend/resume, async I/O uses, OpenSSL support and cloud clustering.</li>
<li>11.20 Break</li>
<li>11.40 Reverse Proxies, Load-Balancing &amp; Clustering - Part 1<br/>
    Mark Thomas (markt)<br/>
    Apache Tomcat provides many options for expanding a Tomcat installation
    beyond a single instance. In this pair of presentations, Mark will review
    the options for load-balancing requests across multiple instances and for
    replicating session data between those instances. The pros and cons of each
    of the options will be discussed to enable attendees to make the right
    choices for their environment. The presentations will also cover common
    misconceptions and configuration mistakes to enable attendees to avoid those
    pitfalls.</li>
<li>12.40 Lunch</li>
<li>13.40 Reverse Proxies, Load-Balancing &amp; Clustering - Part 2<br/>
    Mark Thomas (markt)<br/>
    See above.</li>
<li>14.40 Tomcat from the Cluster to the Cloud<br/>
    Jean-Frederic Clere (jfclere)<br/>
    Using Tomcat in the cloud like in a cluster requires some work. The
    presentation will look to the problems and solutions to have a distributed
    application running in the cloud. A small cloud of Raspberry PI will be used
    to demo one solution using Kubernetes.</li>
<li>15.40 Break</li>
<li>16.00 Ask Us Anything<br/>
    Mark Thomas (markt),  Rémy Maucherat (remm) and Jean-Frederic
    Clere (jfclere)<br/>
    This is your opportunity to ask Mark, Rémy and Jean-Frederic anything about
    working with Apache Tomcat. In addition to being able to ask any questions
    that occur to you during the day, there will be an opportunity to provide
    your questions in advance during this registration process.</li>
</ul>

<p>See you there!</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Thanks">

<p>This event is sponsored by Liferay, the robust java-based
<a href="https://web.liferay.com/community/liferay-projects/liferay-portal/overview"
target="_blank">open source platform</a> (5 million downloads) used to build
sophisticated transactional websites and deliver them to web browsers and native
mobile clients. Liferay, Inc provides enterprise support for the commercial
release which is used by organisations such as Allianz, Volkswagen Group and the
NHS.</p>

<a href="https://www.liferay.com/?utm_source=asf%20tomcat%20uk&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_content=explore%20liferay"
target="_blank"><img src="/res/images/liferay.png" width="200"/></a>

<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.c2b2.co.uk/">c2b2</a> for providing sponsorship
for speaker travel and associated expenses.</p>

<a href="https://www.c2b2.co.uk/"
target="_blank"><img src="/res/images/c2b2.gif" width="125"/></a>

<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en">Red Hat</a> and
<a href="https://pivotal.io/">Pivotal</a> for donating the speakers' time.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Previous events">

<p>Slides along with audio and video (where available) from previous events are
   available from the <a href="presentations.html">previous presentations</a>
   page.</p>

</subsection>

</section>

</body>
</document>
