<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Find Help</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Find help">

<p>Apache Tomcat support is provided by the community, for the community, on a
purely volunteer basis. This page has been written to help you find the help you
need whilst making the most efficient use of the resources available. The types
of help are presented in the same order they are typically used.</p>

<p>The first resource to check is the documentation. In addition to the Tomcat
documentation (make sure you check the documentation for the version you are
using) you should also check the relevant Servlet and/or JSP
<a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/Specifications">Specification</a> documents.
Much of Tomcat's behaviour is determined by these specifications and the information in
them is not typically duplicated in the Tomcat documentation.</p>

<p>The documentation is searchable &#x2013; see input box at the top of the
page. To limit results to a specific major version of Apache Tomcat you can
add the number to the search string, wrapping it in quotes, e.g. "7.0".</p>

<p>The logs which Apache Tomcat generates can be a valuable resource when trying
to diagnose a problem. Please review them. You may want to enable debug output
in your Apache Tomcat configuration so that you have more information to help
diagnose the problem.</p>

<p>It is unusual to find a problem that has never been reported.  The chances are
that your question has been asked and answered by somebody else. Use your
favourite search engine to try and find it.</p>

<p>Answers to very common questions are documented on the
<a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/FAQ">FAQ</a>.</p>

<p>The archives for the user mailing list are a rich source of useful
information. Use the search features provided by one of them. A
<a href="lists.html">selection of archives</a> is provided on the mailing list
page.</p>

<p>If you have already subscribed to the relevant mailing list,
you can ask about the problem on there.  If you are not subscribed, you
will need to subscribe before you can send your question to either of these
lists. The <a href="lists.html">mailing list</a> pages provide further
information on how to use the mailing lists as well as subscription
instructions.</p>

<p>If you have found a bug or propose an enhancement, follow the documented
<a href="bugreport.html">bug reporting</a> steps. Please note, that Bugzilla
is not a support forum. If you need help with your problem, use the users
<a href="lists.html">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p>There is also an <a href="irc.html">IRC channel</a> dedicated to Tomcat.</p>

<p>A number of <a href="presentations.html">Tomcat presentations</a> are
available from past Apache conferences and other sources.</p>

<p>A list of organisations that provide support and training for Apache Tomcat
is maintained on the
<a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/SupportAndTraining">Tomcat Wiki</a>.</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
