<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Get Involved</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Get Involved">

<p>If you would like to become involved in the development and support of Apache
Tomcat there are many different ways in which you can contribute. The first step
is to <a href="lists.html">join the mailing lists</a>. The following are just a
few areas ways in which you can help:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Answer questions posted to the <a href="lists.html">mailing lists</a>.
      </li>
  <li>Contribute to the <a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/FAQ">FAQ</a> or
      <a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/FrontPage">Wiki</a>.</li>
  <li>Contribute other documentation patches, either for the website or for the
      Apache Tomcat user documentation.</li>
  <li><a href="https://bz.apache.org/bugzilla/">Investigate bugs</a> that have
      been reported and provide patches where appropriate.</li>
  <li>Help with development for the next release of the Servlet and JSP
      specifications.</li>
</ul>

You should also read
<a href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html">How Apache Works
</a>.

</section>

<section name="Contributing Changes">

<p>
If you want to start contributing changes, then the first step is to checkout the source
code and build Apache Tomcat. See the <em>Building</em> page in the documentation area for the
version of Apache Tomcat you want to work with for detailed instructions.
</p>

<p>
When making a contribution, minimize unnecessary or unrelated changes (such as formatting).
Apache Tomcat has many contributors, and being able to diff changes throughout the source history is important.
Making small gradual changes and respecting the conventions of the existing source code
will make it much more likely that your patch will be accepted.
</p>

<p>
Once you've got Apache Tomcat up and running, then the Apache 
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dev/contributors.html">Contributors Tech Guide</a> is a good place
to learn how to create and submit patches.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Coding Conventions">
Apache Tomcat has very loosely defined coding conventions, but the following guidelines will be useful:
<ul>
  <li>Use spaces for indenting, not tabs</li>
  <li>100 char line width for Java source, 80 char line width for
      documentation source (.txt, .xml)</li>
  <li>Java source: { at end of line, 4 space indents</li>
  <li>XML source: 2 space indents</li>
</ul>
</section>

</body>
</document>
