<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Apache Tomcat Project</author>
    <title>Apache Tomcat APR/native Connector vulnerabilities</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

  <section name="Apache Tomcat APR/native Connector vulnerabilities">
    <p>This page lists all security vulnerabilities fixed in released versions
       of Apache Tomcat APR/native Connector. Each vulnerability is given a
       <a href="security-impact.html">security impact rating</a> by the Apache
       Tomcat security team &#x2014; please note that this rating may vary from
       platform to platform. We also list the versions of Apache Tomcat APR/native
       Connectors the flaw is known to affect, and where a flaw has not been
       verified list the version with a question mark.</p>

    <p><strong>Note:</strong> Vulnerabilities that are not Tomcat vulnerabilities
       but have either been incorrectly reported against Tomcat or where Tomcat
       provides a workaround are listed at the end of this page.</p>

    <p>This page has been created from a review of the Apache Tomcat archives
       and the CVE list. Please send comments or corrections for these
       vulnerabilities to the <a href="security.html">Tomcat
       Security Team</a>.</p>

  </section>

  <section name="Not a vulnerability in the Apache Tomcat APR/native Connector">
    <p><strong>TLS SSL Man In The Middle</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2009-3555</cve></p>

    <p>A vulnerability exists in the TLS protocol that allows an attacker to
       inject arbitrary requests into an TLS stream during renegotiation.</p>
    
    <p>The TLS implementation used by Tomcat varies with connector. The
       APR/native connector uses OpenSSL.</p>
       
    <p>The APR/native connector is vulnerable if the OpenSSL version used is
       vulnerable. Note: Building with OpenSSL 0.9.8l will disable all
       renegotiation and protect against this vulnerability.</p>

    <p>From 1.1.18 onwards, client initiated renegotiations are rejected to
       provide partial protection against this vulnerability with any OpenSSL
       version.</p>
       
    <p>Users should be aware that the impact of disabling renegotiation will
       vary with both application and client. In some circumstances disabling
       renegotiation may result in some clients being unable to access the
       application.</p>

    <p><strong>Important: Remote Memory Read</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2014-0160</cve> (a.k.a. "Heartbleed")</p>

    <p>A bug in certain versions of <a href="www.openssl.org">OpenSSL</a>
        can allow an unauthenticated remote user to read certain contents of
        the server's memory. Binary versions of tcnative 1.1.24 - 1.1.29
        include this vulnerable version of OpenSSL. tcnative 1.1.30 and later
        ship with patched versions of OpenSSL.</p>

    <p>An explanation of how to deterine whether you are vulnerable and what
        steps to take, see the Tomcat Wiki's
        <a href="https://wiki.apache.org/tomcat/Security/Heartbleed">Heartbleed</a>
        page.</p>

    <p>This issue was first announced on 7 April 2014.</p>

    <p>Affects: OpenSSL 1.0.1-1.0.1f, tcnative 1.1.24-1.1.29</p>
  </section>
</body>
</document>

