<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Apache Tomcat Project</author>
    <title>Security Impact Levels</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Summary of security impact levels for Apache Tomcat">
    <p>The Apache Tomcat Security Team rates the impact of each security flaw
       that affects Tomcat. We've chosen a rating scale quite similar to those
       used by other major vendors in order to be consistent. Basically the goal
       of the rating system is to answer the question "How worried should I be
       about this vulnerability?".</p>

    <p>Note that the rating chosen for each flaw is the worst possible case
       across all architectures. To determine the exact impact of a particular
       vulnerability on your own systems you will still need to read the security
       advisories to find out more about the flaw.</p>

    <p>We use the following descriptions to decide on the impact rating to give
       each vulnerability:</p>

  </section>

  <section name="Critical">
    <p>A vulnerability rated with a Critical impact is one which could
       potentially be exploited by a remote attacker to get Tomcat to execute
       arbitrary code (either as the user the server is running as, or root).
       These are the sorts of vulnerabilities that could be exploited
       automatically by worms.</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Important">
    <p>A vulnerability rated as Important impact is one which could result in
       the compromise of data or availability of the server. For Tomcat this
       includes issues that allow an easy remote denial of service (something
       that is out of proportion to the attack or with a lasting consequence),
       access to arbitrary files outside of the context root, or access to files
       that should be otherwise prevented by limits or authentication.</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Moderate">
    <p>A vulnerability is likely to be rated as Moderate if there is significant
       mitigation to make the issue less of an impact. This might be because the
       flaw does not affect likely configurations, or it is a configuration that
       isn't widely used, or where a remote user must be authenticated in order
       to exploit the issue. Flaws that allow Tomcat to serve directory listings
       instead of index files and cross-site scripting issues are included here.
       </p>
  </section>

  <section name="Low">
    <p>All other security flaws are classed as a Low impact. This rating is used
       for issues that are believed to be extremely hard to exploit, or where an
       exploit gives minimal consequences.</p>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

