<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Apache Tomcat Project</author>
    <title>Apache Tomcat 3.x vulnerabilities</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

  <section name="Apache Tomcat 3.x vulnerabilities">
    <p>This page lists all security vulnerabilities fixed in released versions
       of Apache Tomcat 3.x. Each vulnerability is given a
       <a href="security-impact.html">security impact rating</a> by the Apache
       Tomcat security team &#x2014; please note that this rating may vary from
       platform to platform. We also list the versions of Apache Tomcat the flaw
       is known to affect, and where a flaw has not been verified list the
       version with a question mark.</p>

    <p>Please note that Tomcat 3 is no longer supported. Further vulnerabilities
       in the 3.x branches will not be fixed. Users should upgrade to 7.x or
       later to obtain security fixes.</p>

    <p>Please send comments or corrections for these vulnerabilities to the
       <a href="security.html">Tomcat Security Team</a>.</p>

  </section>

  <section name="Not fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.x">
    <p><strong>Important: Denial of service</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2005-0808</cve></p>

    <p>Tomcat 3.x can be remotely caused to crash or shutdown by a connection
       sending the right sequence of bytes to the AJP12 protocol port (TCP 8007
       by default). Tomcat 3.x users are advised to ensure that this port is
       adequately firewalled to ensure it is not accessible to remote attackers.
       There are no plans to issue a an update to Tomcat 3.x for this issue.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.4, 3.3a-3.3.2</p>

    <p><strong>Low: Session hi-jacking</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2007-3382</cve></p>

    <p>Tomcat incorrectly treated a single quote character (') in a cookie
       value as a delimiter. In some circumstances this lead to the leaking of
       information such as session ID to an attacker.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.3-3.3.2</p>

    <p><strong>Low: Cross site scripting</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2007-3384</cve></p>

    <p>When reporting error messages, Tomcat does not filter user supplied data
       before display. This enables an XSS attack. A source patch is available
       from the <a
       href="https://archive.apache.org/dist/tomcat/tomcat-3/v3.3.2-patches/src/">
       archives</a>.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.3-3.3.2</p>

    <p><strong>Low: Session hi-jacking</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2007-3385</cve></p>

    <p>Tomcat incorrectly handled the character sequence \" in a cookie value.
       In some circumstances this lead to the leaking of information such as
       session ID to an attacker.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.3-3.3.2</p>

  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.3.2">
    <p><strong>Moderate: Cross site scripting</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2003-0044</cve></p>

    <p>The root web application and the examples web application contained a
       number a cross-site scripting vulnerabilities. Note that is it
       recommended that the examples web application is not installed on
       production servers.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.4, 3.3a-3.3.1a</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.3.1a">
    <p><strong>Important: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2003-0043</cve></p>

    <p>When used with JDK 1.3.1 or earlier, web.xml files were read with
       trusted privileges enabling files outside of the web application to be
       read even when running under a security manager.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.4, 3.3a-3.3.1</p>

    <p><strong>Important: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2003-0042</cve></p>

    <p>URLs containing null characters could result in file contents being
       returned or a directory listing being returned even when a welcome file
       was defined.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.4, 3.3a-3.3.1</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.3.1">
    <p><strong>Important: Denial of service</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2003-0045</cve></p>

    <p>JSP page names that match a Windows DOS device name, such as aux.jsp, may
       cause the thread processing the request to become unresponsive. A
       sequence of such requests may cause all request processing threads, and
       hence Tomcat, to become unresponsive.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.4, 3.3a</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.3a">
    <p><strong>Moderate: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2002-2007</cve></p>

    <p>Non-standard requests to the sample applications installed by default
       could result in unexpected directory listings or disclosure of the full
       file system path for a JSP.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.2.3-3.2.4</p>

    <p><strong>Low: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2002-2006</cve>,
       <cve>CVE-2000-0760</cve></p>

    <p>The snoop servlet installed as part of the examples includes output that
       identifies the Tomcat installation path. There are no plans to issue a an
       update to Tomcat 3.x for this issue.</p>

    <p>Affects:3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.4</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.2.4">
    <p><strong>Moderate: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2001-1563</cve><br/></p>

    <p>No specifics are provided in the vulnerability report. This may be a
       summary of other issues reported against 3.2.x</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.2?, 3.2.1, 3.2.2-3.2.3?</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.2.2">
    <p><strong>Moderate: Cross site scripting</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2001-0829</cve></p>

    <p>The default 404 error page does not escape URLs. This allows XSS
       attacks using specially crafted URLs.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.1</p>

    <p><strong>Moderate: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2001-0590</cve></p>

    <p>A specially crafted URL can be used to obtain the source for JSPs.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0, 3.1-3.1.1, 3.2-3.2.1</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.2">
    <p><strong>Low: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2000-0759</cve></p>

    <p>Requesting a JSP that does not exist results in an error page that
       includes the full file system page of the current context.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.1</p>

    <p><strong>Important: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2000-0672</cve></p>

    <p>Access to the admin context is not protected. This context allows an
       attacker to mount an arbitary file system path as a context. Any files
       accessible from this file sytem path to the account under which Tomcat
       is running are then visible to the attacker.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.1</p>
  </section>

  <section name="Fixed in Apache Tomcat 3.1">
    <p><strong>Important: Information disclosure</strong>
       <cve>CVE-2000-1210</cve></p>

    <p>source.jsp, provided as part of the examples, allows an attacker to read
       arbitrary files via a .. (dot dot) in the argument to source.jsp.</p>

    <p>Affects: 3.0</p>
  </section>

</body>
</document>

