<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Apache Tomcat Project</author>
    <title>Apache Taglibs</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Apache Taglibs">
      <p>Apache Taglibs provides open source implementations of Tag Libraries for use with
        Java Server Pages (JSPs). In particular, it hosts the Apache Standard Taglib, an
        open source implementation of the
        <a href="https://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=52">Java Standard Tag Library (JSTL)</a>
        specification.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Apache Standard Taglib">
      <p>The Apache Standard Taglib implements JSTL 1.2 and supports request-time expressions
        that are evaluated by the JSP container.
      </p>

      <p>In addition, compatibility for applications using 1.0 expression language tags can
        be enabled in one of two ways:
      </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Using the <b>-jstlel</b> jar supports JSTL 1.0 EL expressions by using the EL
            implementation originally defined by JSTL itself.
          </li>
          <li>Using the <b>-compat</b> jar supports JSTL 1.0 EL expressions by using the
            container's implementation of EL to take advantage of newer functionality and
            potential performance improvements in more modern versions.
          </li>
        </ul>

      <p style="text-align: center;">
        <a href="download-taglibs.cgi">Download</a> |
        <a href="taglibs/CHANGES.txt">Changes</a>
      </p>

      <p>Please see the <a href="https://www.apache.org/dist/tomcat/taglibs/taglibs-standard-1.2.5/README_bin.txt">README</a>
      file for more detailed information on using the library.</p>

      <p>For performance reasons the XML tags use Apache Xalan directly for evaluating XPath
        expressions. The Xalan 2.7.1 implementation jars xalan.jar and serializer.jar must be
        added to the classpath.
      </p>

      <p>The Standard Taglib jars may be packaged with a web-application in its /WEB-INF/lib
        directory, or may be made available to all applications in a container by adding them
        to the container's classpath.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Jakarta Taglibs">
      <p>Apache Taglibs were originally developed as part of the Apache Jakarta project.
        That project has
        <a href="http://attic.apache.org/projects/jakarta-taglibs.html">officially been retired</a>
        and the original tag libraries moved to the
        <a href="http://attic.apache.org/">Apache Attic</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

